{"tossups": [{"question": "Thiourea catalysts rely on these phenomena to accelerate reactions. The tetrahedral intermediate formed in the chymotrypsin mechanism is stabilized by these phenomena in the oxyanion hole. In solution, carboxylic acid dimers occur because of these phenomena. The Grotthuss mechanism involves diffusion through a network of them. Polar solvents that do not exhibit these phenomena, like DMF and DMSO, are favorable for SN2 reactions. Molecules that exhibit them, such as ethanol, have extremely broad peaks to the left of 3000 wavenumbers on an IR diagram. Three of them occur between guanine and cytosine and two occur between adenine and thymine. The existence of these phenomena explains why ice floats and why water has an unusually high heat capacity. For 10 points, name these intermolecular bonds formed by a namesake element.", "answer": "hydrogen bonds [or H bonds] ", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>hydrogen</u></b> bonds [or <b><u>H bonds</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["hydrogen bonds", "hydrogen", "H bonds"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The title character of a poem by this author keeps his wife \"in his mammoth fold\" and fastens his children in the pen on an election day back when \"people were not democrats\". Another of his poems describes \"gulfs enchanted... where the cold sea-maids rise to sun their streaming hair\". This author of \"The Dorchester Giant\" and coiner of the term \"Boston Brahmin\" praised a \"meteor of the ocean air\" whose \"thunders shook the mighty deep\" in a poem whose speaker exclaims, \"Tear her tattered ensign down!\". This poet described a \"ship of pearl\" in a poem in which he hears a voice singing, \"Build thee more stately mansions, O my soul\". For 10 points, name this author of \"Old Ironsides\" and \"The Chambered Nautilus\".", "answer": "Oliver Wendell Holmes, Sr.", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Oliver Wendell Holmes, <b><u>Sr.</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Oliver Wendell Holmes, Sr.", "Sr."], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A pharmaceutical company in this city accidentally contaminated polio vaccines with live polio virus, infecting thousands of children with the virus in the Cutter Incident. Protesters mourning the death of James Rector were bombed with tear gas canisters dropped from helicopters in this city's People's Park. In 1974, the Symbionese Liberation Army abducted Patty Hearst from her apartment in this city. In one photo taken in this city, suit-clad students march through Sather Gate holding a poster reading \"Free Speech\". Mario Savio delivered the \"Bodies Upon the Gears\" speech on the steps of Sproul Hall in this city, which two years earlier saw the triumph of the Free Speech Movement. For 10 points, name this city home to the flagship campus of the University of California.", "answer": "Berkeley", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Berkeley</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Berkeley", "Berkeley"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This piece begins with two quarter note Gs and a mordent on A. It includes a canon at the unison, a canon at the second, and so on, all the way up to a canon at the ninth. The last movement of this piece is marked \"da capo\", and is thus an exact repeat of its first movement. A slow section of this piece in G minor, the parallel key, was described as its \"black pearl\" by Wanda Landowska (Vanda lan-DOFF-skah), who was the first to record it on period instrumentation. This piece's definitive recording was made by Canadian pianist Glenn Gould. It ends with a quodlibet, has a canon every three movements, and begins with an aria written to cure the insomnia of Count Keyserlingk. For 10 points, name this collection of variations for harpsichord written by J. S. Bach.", "answer": "Goldberg Variations [or Goldberg-Variationen]", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Goldberg</u></b> Variations [or <b><u>Goldberg-Variationen</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Goldberg Variations", "Goldberg", "Goldberg-Variationen"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In her book on these things, Sissela Bok, the daughter of Gunnar Myrdal, writes about the \"publicity test\". In his 1797 periodical France, the philosopher Benjamin Constant defended the right of people to create these things. An 1873 essay whose title has these things as the second noun claims that \"a mobile army of metaphors\" and metonyms is the definition of truth. Kant's response to Constant described the supposed right to create them \"from benevolent motives\", instead arguing these things were always a violation of the principle of right, even if there was a murderer at your door. Nietzsche wrote an essay about truth and these things \"in a nonmoral sense\". For 10 points, Augustine defined what things as words that are said \"with purpose to deceive?\".", "answer": "lies [or obvious equivalents]", "category": "Philosophy", "subcategory": "Philosophy", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>lies</u></b> [or <b><u>obvious equivalents</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["lies", "lies", "obvious equivalents"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This man's cunning is heavily played up in Jacob Robinson's book And the Crooked Shall Be Made Straight. He claimed that Lolita was \"quite an unwholesome book\" after being given it for relaxation purposes. A former traveling salesman for the Vacuum Oil Company, he was \"blown into History\", according to a study. A book about this man argues that he was a joiner, noting his attempts to join groups like the Schlaraffia and Wandervogel. That book controversially called him a more of a \"clown\" and peripheral bystander, not a monster. That book named for this man also argued that he was inherently unremarkable and introduced the phrase \"banality of evil\". For 10 points, Hannah Arendt analyzed the trial of what former Nazi in Jerusalem?", "answer": "Adolf Eichmann (IKE-mahn) [or Otto Adolf Eichmann; or Eichmann in Jerusalem: A Report on the Banality of Evil ", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Adolf Eichmann [or Otto Adolf Eichmann; or Eichmann in Jerusalem: A Report on the Banality of Evil</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Adolf Eichmann [or Otto Adolf Eichmann; or Eichmann in Jerusalem: A Report on the Banality of Evil", "Adolf Eichmann [or Otto Adolf Eichmann; or Eichmann in Jerusalem: A Report on the Banality of Evil"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "IKE-mahn"}, {"question": "A finite extension field is described by this adjective if it is a separable splitting field over its base field. A topological space possesses this separation property if for any pair of disjoint closed subsets there exist two disjoint open sets each of which contains one of the closed sets. Ideals are the ring- theoretic analogues of subgroups of this type, which have coinciding left and right cosets that form the elements of factor groups. The equation of a plane can be calculated with a point on the plane and this type of vector relative to the plane. The z-score can be used to standardize a probability distribution described by this adjective. For 10 points, give this adjective that names a bell-shaped distribution also called Gaussian.", "answer": "normal", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>normal</u></b>", "acceptable": ["normal", "normal"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In a lyric sequence, this poet wrote that \"death will not appal one who, past doubtings all, waits in unhope\". This poet wrote, \"Well, World, you have kept faith with me\", at the beginning of a poem labeled \"a reflection on my eighty-sixth birthday\". This poet of \"In Tenebris\" and \"He Never Expected Much\" wrote, \"The land's sharp features seemed to be the Century's corpse outleant\", in a poem about a time when \"every spirit upon earth seemed fervourless as I\". In that poem of his, the singing of the title bird conveys \"some blessed Hope, whereof he knew and I was unaware\". For 10 points, name this Victorian poet of \"The Darkling Thrush\" also known for such novels as Far from the Madding Crowd and Tess of the d'Urbervilles.", "answer": "Thomas Hardy", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Thomas <b><u>Hardy</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Thomas Hardy", "Hardy"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The governor of an occupied territory in this war garnered support by immediately promising all of his subjects a free color television to watch the World Cup. Peter Holdgate's photograph of a marine with a flag attached to his radio aerial, The Yomper, was taken during this war. In the Black Bucks raids, one side in this war used Vulcan Bombers to destroy an enemy airfield. Torpedoes from a nuclear submarine sunk the General Belgrano during this conflict. Fighting at Goose Green preceded the fall of Port Stanley in this war, causing an effective end of hostilities and the resignation of Leopoldo Galtieri from office. For 10 points, name this war in which British troops were ordered by Margaret Thatcher to reclaim an archipelago from Argentina.", "answer": "Falklands War [or South Atlantic War; or Guerra del Atla\u0301ntico Sur]", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Falklands</u></b> War [or <b><u>South Atlantic War</u></b>; or <b><u>Guerra del Atla\u0301ntico Sur</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Falklands War", "Falklands", "South Atlantic War", "Guerra del Atla\u0301ntico Sur"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The Franciscan friar Francesco Calcagno was executed for suggesting that this book features a homoerotic relationship between two men. In an odd aside near the end of this book, the author refutes the claim that a man would never die, analyzing the phrase \"if it is my will that he remain until I come, what is that to you?\". Theories regarding the identity of a mysterious, unnamed person in this book include Lazarus, Mary Magdalene, and the host of the Last Supper. That figure in this book is told \"Here is your mother\" by Jesus at the crucifixion, referring to the Virgin Mary. Prominently featuring the \"beloved disciple\", this book begins with the line \"In the beginning was the word\". For 10 points, what gospel is believed to be written by a son of Zebedee and is a non-synoptic text?", "answer": "Gospel According to John", "category": "Religion", "subcategory": "Religion", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Gospel According to John</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Gospel According to John", "Gospel According to John"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This province was home to tribes such as the Lillooet who lived in pithouses called quigglies. The Dakelh, or Carrier people in the interior of this province traded in nutritious oolichan fat using \"grease trails\". Salmon fishways were built after rail construction obstructed flow through this province's Hells Gate. The rape of a Nlaka'pamux (in-kluh-CAP-muh) woman precipitated a war with white miners who had traveled to this province following announcements of gold by governor James Douglas, who later negotiated with Winfield Scott during a conflict over whether Britain or the United States owned the San Juan Islands off the coast of this province. This province's Fraser River passes west of the Canadian Cascades before emptying into the Pacific near Vancouver. For 10 points, name this Canadian province directly north of Washington state.", "answer": "British Columbia", "category": "Geography", "subcategory": "Geography", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>British Columbia</u></b>", "acceptable": ["British Columbia", "British Columbia"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "These buildings are called \"instruments of service\" in a manifesto written by John Entenza. Two headlights from a Ford Model A decorate the stairwell of an International Style building of this type designed by Richard Neutra. Arts &amp; Architecture Magazine sponsored the Eameses to design the eighth of many experimental \"case study\" buildings of this type. Approximately sixty L-shaped examples of these buildings were termed \"Usonian\", by an architect who created one nicknamed the \"steamship\" near the University of Chicago in his Prairie style, and designed a cantilevered one in rural Pennsylvania above a waterfall. For 10 points, identify this type of building, American examples of which include Frank Lloyd Wright's \"Robie\" one and Fallingwater.", "answer": "houses [or homes; or residences] ", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>houses</u></b> [or <b><u>homes</u></b>; or <b><u>residences</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["houses", "houses", "homes", "residences"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The linear stability of a fluid in this configuration is governed by the Orr\u00c2\u2013Sommerfeld equation, which can be used to derive Squire's theorem for this configuration. Dendritic growth and viscous fingering is a feature of a fluid in this configuration in a cell named for Henry Selby Hele-Shaw, of variable-pitch propeller fame. It is used to approximate flow between two cylinders when analyzing Couette flow. Quantum vacuum fluctuations of the electromagnetic field create a small attractive force when this configuration exists in a vacuum. Part of it is replaced by an electrolyte in e-caps. A measure for this configuration is equal to permittivity times area over separation and can be scaled up by including a dielectric inside this configuration. For 10 points, name this configuration used by many capacitors.", "answer": "between parallel plates [or parallel flow; or two-dimensional flow; or flow with no z- component until \"create a small attractive force\" is read]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>between parallel plates</u></b> [or <b><u>parallel flow</u></b>; or <b><u>two-dimensional flow</u></b>; or <b><u>flow with no z- component</u></b> until \"create a small attractive force\" is read]", "acceptable": ["between parallel plates", "between parallel plates", "parallel flow", "two-dimensional flow", "flow with no z- component"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A play by this author calls for an actor to hand a piece of knitting belonging to a deceased woman to a male audience member, making him complicit in the plot of the drama. In that play of his, a man who is in love with the prostitute Vertu dons shoe polish before committing a rape and a murder. A character created by this author refuses to act like Saint Theresa, preferring to remain the bookkeeper while spying on the visitors at an establishment referred to as the House of Illusions. He wrote a drama in which a Bishop, a Judge, and a General are among the clients of Irma, who transforms into the Queen during the course of a violent revolution outside of her brothel. For 10 points, name this French absurdist playwright of The Blacks and The Balcony.", "answer": "Jean Genet", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Jean <b><u>Genet</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Jean Genet", "Genet"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A king of this name and number executed the March Across the Belts as part of his series of attacks on Copenhagen. That king of this name and number House of Palatinate-Zweibru\u0308cken (ts-FYE-brook-en) to rule his country and instigated the Second Northern War after he succeeded Queen Christina in Sweden. Jean-Baptiste de Ville\u0300le (vih-LEL) passed the Anti-Sacrilege Act during the reign of a different monarch of this name and number, who incited a revolution by announcing the Ordinances of Saint- Cloud (san-CLOO). Jules de Polignac (po-leen-YOCK) served as Prime Minister under a king of this name and number, who succeeded his brother Louis XVIII as ruler of France. For 10 points, give this name and number of the monarch who was deposed in the July Revolution.", "answer": "Charles X [prompt on Charles] ", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Charles X</u></b> [prompt on <u>Charles</u>]", "acceptable": ["Charles X", "Charles"], "promptable": ["Charles"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Aminias committed suicide after receiving one of these objects from Adonis. Another one of these objects saves Yamato-takeru from a treacherously-set grassfire. The river Van was created when one of these objects was placed in the mouth of Fenrir. Svafrlami forced the dwarves Dvalinn and Durin to make one of these objects, which was cursed to kill a man every time it was used, named Tyrfing. Amaterasu used one of these objects to create the Three Goddesses of Munakata in a competition with Susanoo. Another one of them was retrieved by Susanoo from the tail of the dragon Orochi and was named Kusanagi. A king received one of these weapons from the Lady of the Lake. For 10 points, name this weapon, one of which Arthur pulls from a stone.", "answer": "swords", "category": "Mythology", "subcategory": "Mythology", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>swords</u></b>", "acceptable": ["swords", "swords"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In a riot against one of these businesses owned by Alexander Contee Hanson in Baltimore in 1812, Light-Horse Harry Lee was severely injured. The German immigrant Wilhelm Pratt fled Baltimore after his business of this type was targeted by participants in the Pratt Street riots. The mythical Argus was the namesake of one of these businesses founded by Kitchen Cabinet member Amos Kendall. An abolitionist who ran one of these businesses was put in Boston's Leverett Street Jail for his own protection against a mob in 1835. A mob in Alton, Illinois, destroyed one of these businesses and killed its its owner. Businesses of this type were run by Elijah Lovejoy and William Lloyd Garrison. For 10 points, name these businesses, exemplified by the New York Tribune.", "answer": "newspapers [prompt on printing press]", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>newspapers</u></b> [prompt on <u>printing press</u>]", "acceptable": ["newspapers", "newspapers"], "promptable": ["printing press"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In this painting, the artist's signature is written on a blade that sits next to a match container and a rolled up newspaper in the foreground. The table in this painting closest to the viewer is connected by a plank to another table on which a glass pitcher atop a silver platter obscures a woman's arm. The woman in this painting also modeled for Edouard Manet's thematically-similar The Plum. This painting, originally titled \"A Sketch of a French Cafe\u0301\", was rechristened in 1893 and shown to English audiences, who reacted with moral outrage. In this painting, the actress Ellen Andre\u0301e wears a white headpiece and stares morosely at an untouched glass of the title alcohol. For 10 points, name this painting by Edgar Degas.", "answer": " L'Absinthe (lob-SANT) [or Glass of Absinthe; or The Absinthe Drinker; or A Sketch of a French Cafe\u0301 until it is read; or Figures at Cafe\u0301 until \"A Sketch of a French Cafe\u0301\" is read]", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>L'Absinthe</u></b> [or <b><u>Glass of Absinthe</u></b>; or <b><u>The Absinthe Drinker</u></b>; or <b><u>A Sketch of a French Cafe\u0301</u></b> until it is read; or <b><u>Figures at Cafe\u0301</u></b> until \"A Sketch of a French Cafe\u0301\" is read]", "acceptable": ["L'Absinthe", "L'Absinthe", "Glass of Absinthe", "The Absinthe Drinker", "A Sketch of a French Cafe\u0301", "Figures at Cafe\u0301"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "lob-SANT"}, {"question": "Tetrahydro\u00c2\u00b7biopterin is a cofactor for aromatic amino acid hydroxylases, AGMO, and the synthase for this molecule. NADPH and O2 undergo redox reactions to produce citrulline and this molecule from arginine by a namesake enzyme that also binds FMN, FAD, heme, and calmodulin. This signaling molecule can be made using neuronal, cytokine-inducible, and endothelial isozymes. This cGMP- stimulating molecule can synergize with Viagra to relax penile smooth muscle and facilitate erections. The cardioprotective effects of nitroglycerine arise from its conversion to this gaseous molecule, which is necessary for vasodilation. For 10 points, name this diatomic gaseous molecule that has one fewer nitrogen than nitrous oxide.", "answer": "nitric oxide [or NO; or nitrogen monoxide]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>nitric</u></b> oxide [or <b><u>NO</u></b>; or <b><u>nitrogen monoxide</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["nitric oxide", "nitric", "NO", "nitrogen monoxide"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The speaker of a poem by this author thinks of \"men like Hawkins, Walter Raleigh, Drake, ancestral murderers and poets, more perplexed in memory now by every ulcerous crime\". In that poem, he described how \"a smell of dead limes quickens in the nose\", representing \"the leprosy of empire\" recalled by the \"disjecta membra\" of the title place. The speaker of another poem by this author alludes to \"the ancient war between obsession and responsibility\" and declares, \"The classics can console. But not enough\". This poet of \"Ruins of a Great House\" and \"Sea Grapes\" included the blind man Seven Seas in an epic poem in which Hector and the fisherman Achille fight for the love of Helen. For 10 points, name this poet from St. Lucia who wrote the epic poem Omeros.", "answer": "Derek Walcott [or Derek Alton Walcott]", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Derek <b><u>Walcott</u></b> [or <b><u>Derek Alton Walcott</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Derek Walcott", "Walcott", "Derek Alton Walcott"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This person implemented the Rolls of Oleron, one of the first European maritime laws. While accompanying this non-Spaniard, the mercenary Mercadier was slain. In a likely false story, this person is said to have penetrated a labyrinth and forced Rosamund Clifford to kill herself. William of Tyre blamed the size of this person's baggage train for a disastrous campaign in the Holy Land. According to Andreas Capellanus, the \"Court of Love\" at Poitiers was where this person and Countess Marie of Champagne taught chivalry. This person legendarily dressed like an Amazon during the failed Second Crusade. A few weeks after her marriage to Louis VII was annulled, she married Henry II. For 10 points, what Duchess of Aquitaine was married to kings of both France and England?", "answer": "Eleanor of Aquitaine ", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Eleanor of <b><u>Aquitaine</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Eleanor of Aquitaine", "Aquitaine"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}], "bonuses": []}